Transcription by CastingWords
Shall we start where we left off?
We were asking, don't we,
why do human beings live this way?
What is the root?
The turmoil, the confusion,
the sorrow behind it all,
conflict, violence,
and so many people offering
different ways of solving the problems,
the Asiatic gurus
and the priests all over the world,
and the new books,
everybody offering a new solution,
a new method,
a new way of solving the problems.
And I am sure this has been going on
for a million years.
Do this and you will be all right,
do that and you will be all right.
But nothing seems to have succeeded
to make man live in order,
happily, intelligently,
without any of these chaotic activities going on.
Right?
Why?
Why can't human beings,
so-called educated,
knowing all the scientific knowledge,
biology, sociology,
everything as now is open to every human being.
Why do we human beings live this way,
in this appalling misery?
Some of them are conscious,
some of them are unconscious,
some of them say,
well, this is all right,
let's only for a few years and I'll die,
it's a jolly good business,
and it doesn't matter.
So, why?
What is the... why?
Well, I've often said that they do it
because it gives them the very sorrow,
the very turmoil,
the very problems themselves,
is the security.
But I'm sure...
I wouldn't...
That doesn't...
No, I don't really think so.
I think people just get used to it.
I mean, they miss anything they're used to,
but that's, you know,
in other people get used to scrap fighting
and, you know,
and they miss it when they don't have it,
but that isn't the primary reason,
in my view,
I mean, why they got started.
What's the primary reason?
That's what we wanted to get at.
That's what we're exploring.
But I just feel that whatever happens,
you get used to it
and you come to miss it after a while
just because you're used to it,
but that doesn't explain why it's there.
You know, I was reading the other day,
some writer saying,
historically, five thousand years,
historically,
there have been five thousand wars,
thousands of people killed,
millions killed,
women crying, you follow?
The whole...
And it's not just...
It's still we are going on.
That's right.
I had the same experience.
I used to...
One time I was working and a guy said to me
that he wanted to go to Vietnam to fight
because otherwise his life was every night at the bar.
That's...
I know, but that isn't the reason.
Why...
No, that's not the reason,
but there's something...
They hold...
We hold on to the conflict and the sorrow.
Yes.
Is it we like it?
No, it's not that we like it,
it's we like...
We almost like not liking it.
There's a kind of orientation,
a kind of...
If I know my conflict,
I know where I'm at.
No, have we all become neurotic?
Yes.
Huh?
The whole thing is neurotic.
Are you saying that?
Yes.
The whole society is neurotic.
Which means entire humanity is neurotic?
I think so.
I mean, this is the argument we have all the time.
Is the society sick or...
And then if you say the society is sick,
what's your judgment?
What's the value you're using for comparison?
Which is yourself who are neurotic.
Right.
So when you are faced with that,
that human beings,
who have lived this way,
and have accepted it for millennia
– there have been saviours,
there have been gurus,
there have been teachers,
there have been...
You follow?
And yet they go on this way.
And you say we're all half crazy,
demented,
from top to bottom,
corrupt,
and I come along like I've come along.
Why?
Why do we do it?
Why do we keep it up?
Why are we crazy?
Right.
I have it in my children.
I say to my children,
this is a sick society.
Look, they spend 50 hours a week
in front of the television box.
That's their whole life.
My children, they laugh at me.
All their friends are doing it.
You know, I'm moving beyond that.
Why?
Yes, why?
Without it, what?
Ah, no, not without it, what?
Why first?
That's what we run into.
No, well, no, that's merely a secondary effect.
Secondary, yes.
You see, I think that we get to depend on it,
as we were saying this morning,
to occupy us and so on,
and Vietnam might seem some release
from the boredom of the pub or whatever,
but that's secondary.
And also, when I go to Vietnam or fight war,
all responsibility is taken away from me.
Somebody else is responsible.
The generals.
Right.
In the old days, people used to think
that war would be a glorious thing, you see,
that when the war started in England,
everybody was in a state of high elation.
Exactly.
They didn't know it was in store, you see.
And they're all united.
Mm-hm.
So, come, why?
Why?
Is it that we have started out on the path
that started out on the wrong path?
That's only part of it.
Or is it the species don't kill themselves,
you know, the animal species,
but we are the species that kill each other?
Right.
So, looking at all this panorama of horror
and misery,
and...
I feel this very strongly because I...
when I travel all over the place,
I see this extraordinary phenomenon going on
in India, in America, here, everywhere.
And I say, why do people live this way,
accept these things, read history,
and no...
You follow?
It is no longer concealed.
They have become cynical.
It's all there.
That's right.
They have become cynical.
Well, nobody believes anything can be done about it.
I mean, that's one point.
Now, that's it.
That's it.
Is it?
No, we feel that we cannot do anything about it.
That's for sure.
That's been an old story.
People say human nature is...
Can never be altered.
Yeah.
I mean, that's not new at all.
It's not new.
No, that's...
but that's certainly true.
People feel, or we feel, I mean, let's not say people,
we feel that, like I said this morning,
that this is the way it is, this is the way we live.
I know, but what...
why don't you change it?
Why don't we change it?
I mean, you see your son looking at the television for 50 hours a day.
Right.
You see your son going off to Vietnam, killed, maimed, blinded.
For what?
Right.
I...
Sorry.
I am sorry.
I am sorry for what I did.
What for?
Off to Vietnam, to Vietnam, to Vietnam.
All right.
peculiar questions.
Well, what?
Well, let me now swim search box
and discover a mysterious object,
which is called the Heimlich Islands.
I am sorry to amaze you.
Yes, two는
You are a saint.
Freud came along, Freud made his studies...
he never set up psychoanalysis as to change people.
He said, we can only study about people.
We'll never help them. I'm not interested.
I know now, I don't have to read Freud or Jung or you...
or anybody, it's there right in front of me.
Right. So now we...
Okay, so let's say we now... that's a good...
we know this, we know this fact about people...
and we also know the fact of the matter is...
that they don't try to change it.
What is preventing them?
Ah, that's a question. They don't... that's another fact.
People have tried to change it in many cases, but they...
Okay, but now let's say that they don't try to change it.
You know, they go to go to the Alzheimer's, they go to...
a dozen ways they have tried to change.
But essentially they are the same.
You see, I think people cannot find out...
how to change human nature, you see.
Is that it?
Well, that's... I mean, at least...
whatever methods have been tried are entirely...
Is that it, or is it the fact that the very nature...
of the way they want to change it...
is part of the process itself?
That's what he's saying.
No, he...
Well, no, but I'm saying both.
I say the first point is that whatever people have tried...
has not been guided by an understanding...
a correct understanding of human nature.
So it's guided by this very process itself, right?
The incorrectness.
Yes, let's take the Marxists who say that human nature...
can be improved, but only when the whole economic...
and political structure has altered.
But then...
They try to alter it, the human nature is the same.
They can't alter it, you see.
Because their human nature is such they can't really alter it.
They've got classes, they started off no wars, you know...
But they're using a mechanical way to make a mechanical change.
I mean, mechanical change to make a mechanical...
Look at it, sir. You take yourself.
Right.
Sorry, to be personal, if I don't mind.
Go ahead.
You be the victim.
I'll be the pig in the middle.
Why don't you change?
Well, I...
And don't... no, don't give explanations.
Well, the feel of it is that...
The immediate feel of it is that there is still...
there is that...
I guess I'd have to say there's some sort of false security or false...
the fragmentation, the immediate pleasures...
that are gotten from the fragmentation.
In other words, the fragmentation...
there's still that movement of fragmentation.
That's how come there's not the change.
There's not seeing the whole thing.
I mean, do you want...
when you say that, are you saying...
a political action, religious action, social action...
all separate, all fighting each other almost...
and we are that?
Right, right.
Is that what you're saying?
Yes, I'm saying that.
I mean, that we keep getting something back from...
we get these immediate pleasures and failures...
frustrations from these...
There's much deeper issue than that.
Yeah, there's more.
I mean, my immediate response is...
why don't I change?
What is it that keeps me from seeing the total?
I don't know.
I keep coming up with a kind of feeling that...
I'm getting something...
I keep getting something from not changing.
No, no.
Is it the entity that wishes to change...
sets the pattern of change...
and therefore the pattern is always the same...
in a different colour?
I don't know if I'm making myself clear.
Can you say it another way?
I want to change.
And I plan out what to change...
how to bring about this change.
The planner is always the same...
but the patterns change.
That's right, yeah.
I have an image of what I want.
No, patterns change.
But I who want to change...
create the patterns of change.
That's right.
Therefore I am the old...
and the patterns are new...
but the old is always conquering the new.
Right.
Of course, when I do that...
I don't feel that I'm the old.
Of course.
I feel that I'm the new.
Yeah, I've got a new idea.
Yeah, but I really don't feel...
that I am involved in that old stuff...
that I want to change.
Just now, after lunch...
you were saying Kabbalah, that thing.
There's a new system.
Say, if you study this...
you will be transformed.
That's right.
This has been said a hundred million times.
Do this and you'll be transformed.
They try to do it...
but the centre is always the same.
But each person who does it...
feels that it's never happened before.
Before, yes.
My experience...
Yes.
through that book...
is entirely different.
But the experience, sir...
is still the same old thing.
Right.
I think that is one of the causes of it.
Well, it's a kind of sleight of hand trick...
whereby the thing which is causing the trouble...
is sort of put into position...
as if it were the thing...
that we're trying to make the change.
You see, it's a deception.
I'm deceiving myself...
all the time by saying...
I'm going to change that...
become that.
Then if it doesn't suit me...
so on and on.
Is that it?
Well, that begins to get at it.
I mean...
Look at yourself and say...
is that it?
You read Hindu...
wait a minute...
Hindu...
some book...
and say, yes, how true that is...
I'm going to live according to that.
But the me that's going to live according...
that's the same old me.
Right.
That's right.
Well, we have this...
we run into this in...
with, let's say, with...
I think that all systems, for instance...
of therapy with patients, for instance...
the patient will say the doctor...
is going to be the one to help him.
Yes.
Right.
And then when they see that that doctor...
is like you...
is like you or is not going to help you...
then there's this...
they're supposed to get better...
they're supposed to be well...
but in fact they've never touched...
that central issue...
which is that I thought that somebody...
could help me.
So then they go to something else...
or they go to something else...
and most of them go to another theory.
Another guru...
Another guru, another type...
whether it's a mind guru or...
This afternoon there was a man there too...
here, talking about a new guru...
you follow, or an old guru.
It's all the same old stuff.
You're really getting at the issue...
the fact that the root...
is this belief that something can help even.
No, no, no.
The root remains the same.
Right?
And we trim the branches.
I think the root is something we don't see...
because we put it in the position...
of the one who is supposed to be seeing.
Yes.
You see...
Say that another way.
We don't see the root...
it's sort of a conjuring trick.
You see, we don't see the root...
because the root is put into the position...
of somebody who would be looking for the root.
Do you see?
I don't know if you see it.
Yes, the root says I'm looking for the root.
Right.
It's like the man who says...
I'm looking for my glasses...
and he's got them on.
I like that Sufi story.
You know the Sufi story...
I'm looking for the key...
you know the word about that...
I'm looking for the key over here...
because it's more...
You know the story about the Sufi...
the guy comes along...
and he's the guy calling around...
under the light post.
And he's looking for...
the guy comes along and says...
what are you doing there?
He says, I'm looking for my key.
He says, would you lose it here?
He says, no, I lost it over there...
but there's more light over here.
You know, we throw the light on the other part.
Yes, sir.
So, if I want to change...
because I don't want to live that way...
I don't want to follow anybody...
because they're all like...
they're like...
the rest of the gang.
I don't accept any authority in all this.
Authority arises only when I'm confused...
when I'm in disorder.
That's right.
So I said, can I completely change...
at the very root?
Well, now you see...
let's look at that...
because you're saying I...
there seems confusion in the language...
because I say I...
Confusion of language, I know.
Which makes it hard because you say...
I'm going to change...
it's not clear what I mean by I.
The I is the root.
The I is the root, so how can I change?
That's the whole point.
You see, the language is confusing...
because you say I've got to change at the root...
but I am the root.
Yes.
So what's going to happen?
No, how am I not to be I?
That's the question.
Well, not...
yes, but what you mean by that?
Yes.
How am I not to be I?
But let's roll it back a minute, a second.
You state you're not going to accept any authority.
Who is my authority?
Who?
They have all told me...
do this, do that, do the other.
Read this book, you'll change.
Follow this system, you'll change.
Become... identify yourself with God, you will change.
But I remain exactly as I was before...
in sorrow, in misery, in confusion...
looking for help...
and I choose the help which suits me most.
Can we stop here for a minute?
What would you say about...
now I mentioned something about psychiatry here...
and I'd like to get something straight if we can.
There is this whole theory...
and gurus have it...
they don't talk about it...
but they have it...
and then there is in all psychiatry...
that is the theory...
that if I go along with the authority...
to where I see my addiction to authority...
then I'll free myself from the authority.
You know that.
Yes, or rather the communists say...
freedom comes at the end of good discipline.
And the discipline is what I tell you.
Right.
Yes, at the end of the dictatorship of the proletariat.
In other words, by giving you...
by bringing myself over...
I will discover my error.
Now, what do you want to say about that?
I mean, isn't that obvious?
Right, it's obvious.
I mean, that I'm doing the same thing...
and then I don't really...
I see the failure of this authority...
but you see, there is a thesis there...
that if I see the particular...
of my following authority...
then I will see the universal in the root.
But why do you have to follow...
the authority to see authority?
See, this is one of the questions, you see.
Do you have to deceive yourself...
in order to understand self-deception?
Yes, sir.
But...
So, is it possible for a human being...
to change at the very root of his being?
They have tried different ways...
different Zen, you follow?
You know, ten different...
umpteen different ways...
they have tried to change man...
rewarding him, punishing him...
promising him.
Nothing has changed...
brought about this miraculous change.
And it is a miraculous change.
It would be, yes, it is.
It is.
Everybody promises...
do this, do that, do the other.
Right.
And I, a man like...
we come along and say, look...
I don't want to accept any authority.
Right.
Because you have misguided everybody...
all the authorities.
Authority...
In itself is disorder.
Right.
Authority exists because...
human beings are in disorder.
The disorder has created them.
Not clarity, not compassion...
not something entirely different.
It is the disorder that has created them.
So why should I follow them?
Though they promise, do this...
discipline yourself according to this way...
ultimately you will be free.
I reject all that.
Not intelligently, because I see.
It isn't a cantankerous rejection.
It is a reasonable rejection.
It is a reasonable, sane rejection.
Uh-huh.
So how do I proceed?
I've got 50 years to live.
I don't know about the future...
maybe I'll find out.
Uh-huh.
But I've got 50 years to live properly.
What is the correct action?
What is the correct action to live properly?
That's all. That's all.
To be sane.
Not to be neurotic.
Who is going to tell me?
The Communists?
Marx?
Lenin?
Mao?
The Pope?
Or the local priests?
Who is going to tell me?
Because they don't act rightly either.
But we have a whole group of people...
who don't say that they'll tell you.
We have a whole group of people who'll say...
who say, see how you follow me...
and see the...
see if you follow me...
see your tendency to follow me...
Yes, yes.
And then...
I understand that.
You have a tendency to see through that.
To see through your own self-deception.
But I mean, that's really an impossible trick, you see.
Because if you say, follow me and deceive yourself...
then you must genuinely deceive yourself...
Right.
and you can't see.
That's right.
But the thesis is that if you deceive yourself...
you will see your own tendency to self-deception...
which you don't see.
But that must be authority.
Because, I mean, it doesn't make sense to say...
that if I deceive myself...
I'm going to see through deceiving myself.
I mean, the whole point of self-deception is that...
if I'm really doing it right...
I don't know what I'm doing.
Right.
Therefore, how do you guarantee to me...
that I can see through self-deception...
by deceiving myself?
Because I'm going to show you through a self...
I'm not going to participate.
I'm going to be here.
And you're going to deceive yourself...
and then you're going to see this authority...
the way you need authority.
You're talking about group therapy.
I'm talking about a kind of psychotherapy.
Psychotherapy.
Right.
But why do I need that?
You see, why do I need to go through all that...
to see self-deception?
It's not clear.
Right.
No, it's not clear.
But that's the only way...
in other words, you're so desperately in need.
You need me desperately.
I don't need you.
No, but he does.
That is fundamentally wrong.
I'm accepting authority, right?
Yes, you're fundamentally...
that's right, but he is fundamentally wrong.
Here he is, he's fundamentally wrong.
So tell him that.
You're fundamentally wrong.
Then he doesn't hear me.
No.
Don't ask him...
don't allow him...
to appeal to you.
You mean don't accept...
don't play along in this absurdity.
I can't help you.
Because I'm like you.
I'll take my trade.
I'll go somewhere else.
So if everybody says I can't help you...
you have to do it yourself, look at yourself...
then the whole thing is beginning to act.
Right.
But the whole thing is not...
doesn't work like that.
There are a lot of people...
who will be willing to deceive him...
for a few dollars.
We know they're all neurotic people.
Right.
Here is a man who says I'm neurotic...
I won't go to any other neurotic...
to become sane.
I know.
So what does he do?
He doesn't accept any authority.
Because I have created out of my disorder...
the authority.
So that's merely the hope...
that somebody knows what to do.
Yes.
You see, it's...
I feel that this chaos is too much for me...
and I just assume that somebody else...
can tell me what to do.
But that comes out of this confusion.
In other words...
Yes, disorder creates the authority.
Of course.
Like in the school I've been saying...
if you behave properly there is no authority.
The behaviour we have all agreed to.
Yes.
Punctuality, cleanliness, this or that.
If you really see it, you have no authority.
Yes, I see that.
That I think is a key point...
that the disorder itself creates the need for authority.
Sir, look what's happened in India.
Mussolini is a perfect example.
Trains run properly.
It doesn't actually create a need for authority...
it creates among people the impression...
that they need authority to...
correct the disorder.
That's it.
Because the authority they don't need at all...
because it's just destructive.
Right.
So, let's start from there.
I reject all this.
Being not insane...
in the rejection of authority...
I have become very sane.
I'm beginning to become sane.
Right.
So, I say, now, I know I'm neurotic.
A human being says, I know.
Now, what shall I do?
What is the correct action in my life?
Can I ever find it, being neurotic?
Right.
I can't.
So, I won't ask what is the right action.
I'll say, now, can I free my mind...
the mind from being neurotic?
Is it possible?
I won't go to Jerusalem...
I won't go to Rome...
I won't go to any new...
Park Avenue, doctors, nobody.
Right.
Because I'm very serious now.
I'm deadly serious because that's my life.
Right.
But then you say, you have to be so serious...
and then you say that in spite of the immense pressure...
to escape...
I won't.
You won't.
But I'm saying that what one will feel at this juncture...
will probably be an intense pressure toward escape.
You see, you're saying this is too much.
No.
No, sir.
You see, what happens...
Actually, that's not what happens.
What happens?
When I reject authority, I have much more energy.
Tremendous energy.
Yes, if you reject it.
Because I'm now concentrated to find out.
That's right.
That is what happens.
I'm not looking to anybody.
That's right.
I know, in other words, then I have to use my...
then I have to really be rawly open to what is.
That's all I've got.
So what shall I do?
When I'm rawly open to what is.
No, I'm not open.
Here is a human being caught in all this.
What shall you do?
No authority?
No social discipline is immoral.
Right?
Then you...
It's the intense alertness to...
No, tell me, tell me, you are a doctor.
Tell me what I am to do.
I reject you.
Right.
Because you're not my doctor.
You are not my authority.
Right.
You don't tell me what to do.
That's right.
Because you are confused.
Right.
So you have no right to tell me what to do.
So I come to you as a friend.
Right.
Say, let's find out.
That's right.
Because you are serious and I'm serious.
Let's see what...
We can work together and...
No, no, no, no, be careful.
I'm not working together.
You're not going to work together.
No.
We are together investigating.
Together investigating.
Okay, we won't call it...
We're investigating together.
No, no, no.
Working together means cooperation.
Right.
I'm not cooperating.
I say you are like me.
That's right.
What am I to cooperate with?
Well, we're cooperatively...
You don't want to cooperatively investigate.
No.
Because you are like me.
That's right.
Confused, miserable, unhappy, neurotic.
Right, right.
So I say, how can we cooperate?
We can only cooperate in neuroticism.
That's right.
You mean we'll collude essentially...
Yes, of course.
...to play, deceive ourselves.
So what are we going to do?
So can we investigate together?
That's a very interesting question.
Can we?
How are we going to investigate together if we're both neurotic?
No.
So I say, look, I'm going to first see in what ways I'm neurotic.
Okay, all right, let's look at it.
Yes, look at it.
In what way am I neurotic?
A human being.
Comes from New York or Tokyo or Delhi or Moscow, wherever.
He says, I know I'm neurotic.
Society is neurotic.
The leaders are neurotic.
And I am part of...
I am the world and the world is me.
So I can't look to anybody.
Exactly.
That gives you what it does.
Well, it really puts you up here.
Straight up there in front.
It gives you a tremendous sense of integrity.
Right.
You've got the ball in your hands now, run with it.
Well...
Now can I, I being a human being, can I look at my neurotic?
Is it possible to see?
My neuroticism.
What is neuroticism?
What makes me neurotic?
All these things they have put into me.
Into me in the sense, the me that has collected all this,
which makes the me.
Can my consciousness empty all that?
Your consciousness is that, though.
Of course.
Is it only that?
For the moment I am limiting it to that.
That is my consciousness.
That very...
The proliferation of my fragmentation or my thought is my neuroticism.
What am I going to do this?
What am I going to get here?
Where am I going to get this?
What am I going to do there?
Or how am I going to...
I mean, this me is made out of the proliferation of these fragments.
Isn't that right?
Yes, of course.
But also this means tremendous question, you follow?
Oh.
Can I, can the consciousness of man,
which began five, ten million years ago,
with all the things that have been put in,
and I have been connected to it,
generation after generation,
from the beginning till now,
you are asking,
all that is neurotic, old boy,
all that is fragmented collection,
can you take one at a time of those and look at it?
Or can you take the whole of it and look?
Yes.
Well, can you take the whole of it and look?
That doesn't, that's not clear.
How can you take the whole of it and look?
Yes, I mean, how...
there seems, I mean, at least a language problem there,
because you say, if you are that,
how are you to look at it?
I'm going to look at it.
I'll show you in a minute.
We'll go into it.
No, but I meant that it is a difficulty of stating it.
Stating it.
I know it's a verbal, you know, the words are wrong, you see.
Right, the words are wrong.
It's a verbal problem.
Because the words are made by this very system there.
Yes.
So we shouldn't take these words too literally.
Too literally, of course.
Could we say that the words can be used flexibly?
Right.
Now that's a good point.
No, the word is not the thing.
That's right.
The word is not the thing,
but the word points at something much bigger than itself.
No, word is not the thing.
It may be the big thing or the little thing,
but the word is not that.
Not that.
Yes, but you see, we are using words,
and the question is, how are we to understand them?
You see that they are in some way,
a clue to what we are talking about.
But it seems to me, you see, that one trouble with the words,
the way we take them,
we take them to mean something very fixed,
like saying...
This is a chair.
This is exactly a chair.
My consciousness is just so, you see.
I am the neurosis.
Therefore we take it very fixed.
It's moving, it's subtle.
It's moving and changing, yes.
And therefore you can't just exactly say,
I am the neurosis or I am not the neurosis.
It is constantly in flux.
But he is saying something bigger,
which is the fact that the very thing that we are investigating
is the way word is...
I mean, the way we use words as the thing
is the very movement that we are investigating.
That is the consciousness.
That's it.
You see?
Would you repeat that once more?
Yes.
That the very act of the word being seen
as the thing by consciousness,
that that very movement is the thing we must investigate.
Of course. Yes.
That is...
Now, can you look at it without the word?
Is that possible?
The word is not the thing.
The word is a thought.
And as a human being I realize I am neurotic.
Neurotic in the sense I believe.
I live in conclusions, in memory,
which are all neurotic processes.
In words.
The words, pictures and reality.
I believe.
That's how you live.
I mean, my belief is very real.
It may be illusory.
All beliefs are illusory.
But because I believe so strongly,
they are real to me.
Right.
They are very real to you.
Very.
So, can I look at that,
the nature of the belief,
how it arose,
look at it?
Look at how I'm living in the world
in which I'm trapped by the belief
in the word is the thing.
Look at that movement.
Don't expand that.
I understand.
Just look at that.
You've got a belief, haven't you?
Oh, yes.
Now, look at it.
Can you look at it?
Well, I saw.
I mean, this morning we were talking about
the fact that the belief is doctor,
word, thing.
Don't expand it.
Can you look at that?
Look at that.
At that fact that you have a belief.
Whatever it is.
God and the state is the most important
or whatever it is.
Right.
Marx is the newest god or Mao
and so on, so on, so on.
But I believe it's true.
No.
Can you look at that belief?
As a belief and not as a fact.
Oh, no.
It's a fact.
It is.
It is a reality to you when you believe in it.
Go to a Catholic, a Hindu or a Marxist.
Well, how am I going to look at it
if I really believe in it?
In other words, look, I say there is a god.
Right?
Right.
Now, you're telling me to look at my belief in the god.
Why do you believe?
Who asked you to believe?
What is the necessity of god?
Not that I'm an atheist.
I'm asking you.
No, it's there.
God is there for me if I believe.
There is no investigation.
You have stopped.
You have blocked yourself.
I've blocked.
You have shut the door.
That's right.
So how are we going to get...
You can't.
Because we've got such beliefs.
Ask him.
Right.
How are we going to get a belief...
You have tried a hundred times to show somebody who is a very strong belief.
Right.
He says, what are you talking about?
This is reality.
That's right.
That's the point.
Yes, well, that's the thing that how our word becomes reality.
Do you see?
Can we investigate that?
That's it.
And how can we get at this?
Because I think we have loads of these unconscious beliefs that we don't really shake, like the
belief in the me.
Yes.
I mean, I think that...
He's asking some other question.
Well, how thought or word becomes a sense of reality.
Do you see that?
Yes.
Why words have become realities?
You see, I think a deeper question is how the mind sets up the sense of reality.
Do you see?
I mean, if I look at things, I may think they are real.
Sometimes mistakenly, you know, and that's an illusion.
But when it comes to the...
And you know, even with objects, you can say a word and it seems real when you describe
it that way.
Right.
And therefore, in some way the word sets up in the brain a construction of reality.
Yes.
And then everything is referred to that construction of reality.
How am I to investigate that?
What created that reality?
Would you say everything that thought has created is reality, except nature?
But thought didn't create nature.
Of course not.
No, but I mean, can't we put it that thought can describe nature?
Yes.
Thought can describe nature, poetry, you know, all the rest of it.
And also measure it.
Imagination, all the rest of it.
Can we say thought, whatever it has put together, is reality?
The chair, the table, all these electric lights.
Nature it hasn't created, but it can describe it.
And also make theories about it.
Make theories and all the rest of it.
And also, the illusion it has created is a reality.
Right.
Yes.
But isn't it, say, to a certain extent this construction of reality has its place, because,
you see, if I feel that the table is real, although the brain has constructed that, it's
okay.
Now, but at some stage we construct realities that are not there, you see.
And we can see this sometimes in the shadows in a dark night, constructing realities that
are not there.
Yes, you see.
And also, all sorts of tricks and illusions are possible by conjurers and all sorts of
things.
Right.
And now, but then it goes further and say mentally we construct a psychological reality.
That's where it comes.
Which seems intensely real, very strong.
But it seems to me the question is what is it that thought does to give that sense of
reality, to construct reality?
Can we watch?
What does thought do, bring about to create that reality?
Yes.
I mean, like if you talk to someone who believes in God, they say to you that's real, that
it's really there, it's not a construction.
And if you talk to somebody who really believes in their self, I mean, I've talked to many
people and you have been talking to the psychotherapist, they say the self is real, that it exists,
it's a thing.
I mean, you heard a man once, he did a psychotherapy, he says to Krishnaji, that we know the ego,
the ego exists.
He says, we've got a theory, it exists.
Well, it's not only that, but see, I think people have felt it's reality and they refer...
What happens is that the illusion builds up very fast.
Once you construct the reality, all sorts of events are referred to it as if they were
coming from that reality, you see.
And it builds up a tremendous structure, a cloud around it of support.
Right.
So how am I to investigate my reality-making mechanism?
Wait, wait, wait.
We have five minutes more.
Oh.
So let's come to it.
I'm going to do it.
What are we doing now?
We're moving.
It's moving.
No, what are we doing?
Invest...
We have said no authority, no... but you can say to another, this is the right thing to
do, because we are trying to find out what is the correct action in life.
I can only find that out if there is no disorder in me.
Right?
Right.
Me is the disorder.
That's right.
However real that me is, that is the source of disorder.
Right.
Because that separates, that divides me and you and we and they and my nation, my God,
me.
Right.
Now we're asking how, with its consciousness...
...how...
Right.
...how can that consciousness be aware of itself?
Aware, like thought thinking.
Thinking about itself?
About thought can... put it very simply, can thought be aware of its own movement?
Yes.
Yes, that's the question.
That's the question.
I mean, it's been called a question.
I mean, it's been called, it could be said, a self-reference of thought to...
Yes.
...thought understanding its own structure, its own movement.
Its own structure, its own movement.
And...
But is that thought that's aware of itself or is it something else?
No, no, no.
Try it, try it.
Try that.
Try...
Do it now.
Four minutes you have.
Right.
Do it now, whether you can be aware of your... not you, when... whether thought can be aware
of itself.
Of itself.
Of...
Okay.
...knowing what is.
Of itself.
But understand thought is because thought is great, it's great, its purpose, it's worth
the effort, it's worth the effort that you put in, is worth the
Evidence whatever it is.
Evidence-
Yes.
It stops.
What does it mean?
It means what it says.
It stops that it can't be, that the sense of… well, the observation of thought, thought
stops.
No, don't put it that way.
How would you put it?
It is undergoing a radical change.
Yes, so the word thought is not a fixed thing.
No.
The word thought…
It does not mean a fixed thing.
Yes.
But it can change, right?
That's right.
In perception.
I mean, you have told me, other scientists have told me, in the very observation through
a microscope, the object…
Yes.
The object undergoes a change.
In the quantum theory, the object is, you know, cannot be fixed apart from the act
of observation.
Well, this is true with patients, in psychoanalysis, being with the patient, they change automatically.
No, forget the patient.
You are the patient.
I am the patient.
It changes.
No, no.
It stops.
What takes place?
What takes place when thought is aware of its own, of itself?
No, sir, this is an extraordinarily important thing.
Yes.
That is, can the doer be aware of his doing?
Can I move this…
vase from here to there?
Can I be aware of that?
Moving.
Yes.
I can, physically, that's very simple.
Right.
I stretch out the arm and so on and so on.
Yes.
But can… is there an awareness of thought which says, yes, I am… I see what's…
thought is aware of itself, its movement, its activity.
Yes.
Its structure, its nature, its… how… what it has created, what it has done in
the world, the misery, the… all the rest of it.
Is there an awareness of the doing of the brain?
Let me ask you something.
Why do you think you can be aware of…
Time.
I want to save that question for tomorrow.
You know the question is…